<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>(Here all may see, that) justice and judgement is to rule. And the power of God without respecting mens persons, or observing the worlds complements. And sheweth how the pure religion keeps out from the spots of the world. ... And sheweth the prisoning for not bowing the hat, is such a thing as hath not been since the world began.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84788</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864291</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116518</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240905210</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E884_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204828</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864291</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864291e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E884[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>(Here all may see, that) justice and judgement is to rule. And the power of God without respecting mens persons, or observing the worlds complements. And sheweth how the pure religion keeps out from the spots of the world. ... And sheweth the prisoning for not bowing the hat, is such a thing as hath not been since the world began.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons at the signe of the Bull and Mouth near Aldersgate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: G.F., i.e. George Fox.</note>
                  <note>The first five words of title are enclosed in square brackets.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 4th."; Aug: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116518:1"/>
            <p>[Here all may see, that] JUSTICE <hi>AND</hi> JUDGEMENT IS TO RULE.</p>
            <p>AND The Power of God without respecting Mens Persons, or observing the Worlds Complements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And sheweth</hi> How the pure Religion keeps out from the Spots of the world. And sheweth how the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is insnared for keeping the Commands of Christ. And sheweth how he is made a Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor for reproving in the Gate, and crying openly gainst sin. And sheweth how <hi>David</hi> bowed the hearts of the People. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.</note> And how all the people that were with <hi>David</hi> the King, had their heads cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, though he was a King. <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> And <hi>Moses</hi> the Judge of all <hi>Israel,</hi> said unto <hi>Aaron, Eleazar,</hi> and <hi>Ithamar, Ʋncover not your Heads, neither rent your Cloaths, least you dye, and wrath come upon all the People.</hi> And shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Prisoning for not bowing the Hat, is such a thing as hath not been since the world began.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Aldersgate.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116518:2"/>
            <head>[Here all may see, That] <hi>Justice</hi> &amp; <hi>Judgement</hi> is to Rule, and the Power of God without respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens Persons, or observing the Worlds Complements.</head>
            <p>ALL you who make plots against the just and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your snares to take them, and seekes deepe to hide your Counsell from the Lord who with your hookes with your baites, with your nets with your snares lies to catch the innocent, Such as doth reprove in the gates which hath departed from iniquity themselves, and reproves the workers of iniquity, these are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a reproach and a bye word and a taunt and hollowed at, shouted at, in Townes Cities and Countries, and such as are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord to reprove such as are given to drunkennesse, swearing lying, cozening and pleasures, these are persecuted in this age as peacebreakers who reproves such as are before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; Now here it is seene what peace is broken, and how equity cannot enter the streets nor Justice run downe but is turned aside, and the King of Righteousnesse and Truth is not here suffered to raigne and such as are brought to exhort people to feare God and to professe no more then what they doe possesse, and that such as live out of the spirit that gave forth the Scriptures should wait for it; for if the other spirit get the Scriptures which gave them not forth it is theft; and for bidding such as steales to steale noe more, but that all might come to the life that gave forth the Scriptures, and live in that which gave them forth, and when this hath been so, then they are accused for duells, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull Language, and here againe all may see what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion you stand in, that hath no more gravity among men, nor no more feeling that cannot endure sound exhortation sound words, nor sound doctrine, what Religion is here; that nothing but words of flattery you can endure and such as cannot sweare who obey the Commands of the Lord, and have the testimony of Jesus profferring to them the oath of abjuration which was for Papists,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116518:3"/>and such as were suspected for Papists and Jesuites, which was not for them that abides in Christs doctrine who cannot sweare at all who keepes the Commands of the Lord and receives his testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelation said the Beast and the Dragon shall make warre aga nst and be wrath, such as keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, have the testimony of Jesus, hath Jesus testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that saith sweare not at all: and to such now is the oath of juration put that cannot sweare at all: and many because they cannot take it, are put into Prison; was ever the like baits hookes and snares (see;) to catch the innocent and such as keepe the Commands of God? and for giving forth a paper against sin and wickednesse, of such now is demanded good behaviour; now had not sin and wickednesse, been cryed against here; here had not been (it seemeth) a breach of good behaviour: Now see how Judgement and Justice is turned backward; and the oath of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration, that is put so much throughout the Nation to friends which obey the commands of the Lord, and many cast into Prison because they cannot sweare, and will not take that Oath which is to be given to the papists and Jesuits, when was ever the oath of abjuration (given) to the Papists or them that are Popishly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected or to the Priests of the Nation but to them that they know cannot take an oath and here are the just made a prey upon; which scarce was such a thing heard of before, and doe you not beleeve that the eye is open that all these things are looked over and the Lord beholds; and the Lords Arme upholds his elect through out all these tribulations; what unchristian life is here before mentioned seene? see what snares baites, nets and hookes heere is to bring out of the commands of the Lord into the evill, into the Condemnation as <hi>James</hi> speakes of out of the yea and nay A Christian life is out of the Condemnation? out of the evill, but who sweares goes above the yea and nay, and so goes into the evill: and who so sweares is fallen into the Condemnation out of the Christians life which is a high life and here all may see what havock and what inventing there is against the Just? and such as live in the spirit of Christ Jesus who comes to doe his will and knowes his doctrine: Now to have that which was made for Papists and (those who are) Popishly affected and Jesuits which can sweare and will sweare; that to be turned against them which cannot sweare or take an Oath who witnesse Christ the Oath of God his everlasting Covenant and promises of God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116518:3"/>fullfilled. Doe not you beleeve that the names of such in ages to come will stink which upon Record will be among them that be in the honourable Christians life? which is not of the world nor of their changing Notion, nor selfe seperation nor feigned humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity not of the Congregation of the dead but such as come to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the Christians life passeth from death to life to Christ the oath of God and here knowes the vine such as are come to yea and nay in all their communications did ever any that was in the Power of Godlinesse persecute, but such as was in the forme of Godlinesse? and againe was there ever such a thing hea d since the world began in all ages past that ever any was persecuted, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned and fined for not doffing their hatts and not swearing which came before any of the heathen the grossest that was the stubbornest as was? for they had hatts in the dayes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Children of the Lord which could not bow to the Image, was cast into the fiery furnace with their hats on but we see they were not cast in for not doffing their hats neither was any cast in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Prison among the holy men of God nor the heathen but we see <hi>Mordechai</hi> which could not bow to <hi>Haman</hi> was like to be slain and put to death not him only but all the <hi>Jewes</hi> that feared God which could not obey the Kings Command these could not obey man his commandement nor the three Children could not obey <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> concerning his Image, nor <hi>Mordechai</hi> could not obey the Kings Command and was that the Type of this great Substance now in this age the hat the not bowing it? which not bowing it so many are cast into Prison, and great fines of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Cast upon them, now that the hat this base thing a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement among the world the not bowing the hatt, theis base thing a Complement of the world should confound all the Religion of the world yea and Justice as they call in the world that there is no Justice except the hat be bowed among them that fear not God is not this the Beast, is not this the Image of the Beast and the Beast that there is noe Justice except the hat be bowed? is not this the mark of the Beast that there is no equity done except they will receive his marke yea or nay, was ever the unchristian state got to such a height was it ever so in all ages that Justice stood in a hat? for want of a hat that should have been on; or that the hat should overthrow Justice and was it ever so in all ages past that a hatt should overthrow Religion; and doth not the Lord here with a base thing confound the wise and the mighty and with a thing which is not bring to nought the things
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116518:4"/>that are and is not all this a dishonur to a Christians life, and practice and shewes that their striving about those things before mentioned as hatts that they are out of the Christians life; doth not the pure Religion keep out of the world and the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it unipotted of them, and is not a hat of the world a complement and is not all the world spotted with it, serving and bowing and worshiping the Creature more then the Creator and what is it to give the glory to the Beast which all the world wonders after and worships and is the soule to be subject to the higher power or to the hatt and doth the Royall Law of God respect any mans person or a hat and is not he that doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced to be a transgressor (mark and take notice) and are not the weighty matters of the Law neglected Judgement faith and mercy, while the hat is so much wrangled at among men that are respecting one anothers persons? doth not it manifest here that all that are striving for the hatt to be bowed to them or else to be disturbed they to be such that hath the old Garment on and the convering which is not with the spirit of the Lord to which the woe belongs and doth not all that be in this state dishonour the Truth dishonour Religion, dishonour Justice yea the higher power which the soule must be subject to and the Royall Law which respects no mans persons but brings to the Lord is not the hat an Image and except you will give him that Image the hat there is somthing in man rages, what is that mark &amp; take notice is it not a work of mens hands? are they all blind is there none tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from Images doth none love Justice; yea and the Lord is set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that up and establishing Justice in the earth and his power shall raise it up above the world, and above the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and above him that abode not in the truth but is out of it; and all the Inventions of them that be out of the truth and is not the pure Religion dshonoured which keepeth not to be spotted with the world (marke) as I said before is not the bowing of the hatt the worlds Complement and the worlds fashion that passeth away and the worlds worship which makes the heathen to rage if the hatt be not bowed; doth not the pure Religion which keepes unspotted from the world, keepe from the worlds fashions the worlds Complement the worlds worships and doth not the pure Religion keep from the spots of the world, &amp; whether the worlds fashions complements customs worships wil not spot, whether men striving for these things the hat bowing while they are striving for these doe not forget the weightier matters Judgement mercie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116518:4"/>and righteousnes, &amp; strive for them that doth spot. Now whether these things doth not give a stinke among them that act Justice without respect of persons, and whether it be not a griefe to them that doe Justice and equity without respect of any mans person to be such whose eye is altogether at the hatt for bowing, whether this is not the eye that would have persons respected, yea or nay that is blind in the things of God, a man coming into the Court with his hatt on soberly, not bowing his hatt he that saith be disturbs all the Court whether this is not the eye that would have the person respected, &amp; which in this mean time is not Justice and Judgement, and mercy neglected which are the weightier matters of the Law and faith, for he that saith if you will not bow the hatt I will not doe you Justice; is not the hatt weightier then the Justice is not Justice to be done without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of persons (mark that) persons is more then a hatt, nor he that will doe Justice with respect of an hatt, if the hatt be bowed and not else is not here Justice done with respect of persons; now he that will not doe Justice without respect of a hatt and without respect of persons is not that honourable in the sight of God and them that feare him; whether is the person or the hatt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test to be respected seeing that Justice must be done without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of persons and they that will not doe Justice without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of an hatt the respect of a person is greater, let but reason Judge of this was them that did Justice with respect of persons in ages past a tipe of this age? which now of such as will not Judge without respect of an hatt is this the great substance of that tipe? for this is a thing brought forth which is beyond all them that ever was acted in the Scriptures either among the heathen or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the holy men of God since the world beganne if that you can shew an example declare it to them who lies fined and Prisoned for not bowing of the hatt and therefore hath not Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and witnesseth the pure Religion which keepes from the worlds spots whose soul is to the higher Power subject who witnes the weightier matters of the Law faith Judgement and mercy, and rejoyceth in them that walke humbly with God and loves Justice and mercy, whose soules to the higher power is subject not for wrath but for Conscience sake, who rejoyceth in that sword that is turned against the evill doer, who is for the praise of them that doe well, who owns every Ordinance of man, which is for the Lords sake, which is for the punishment of the evil doer, a lover of righteousnes in the establishing of it w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> answereth the righteous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116518:5"/>principle in every man who suffers because they can't bow the hat which is one of the worlds Complements &amp; worship man &amp; serve the Creature more then the Creator who is God blessed for ever therefore to whom Justice was not done here the hat was respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as in former time the person hath been respected in Judgment which now is more then was ever and the hatt respected which shewes you in the transgression of the Law of God and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er power, for is any one soule subject to the higher power that respects either hatt or person and will not Judge without the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the hatt and person is his soule subject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er yea or nay Consider is not he that is full of prejudice wrath rage &amp; fury out of the fear of God who respects the hat, when it is so, when to himit is not bowed, is not this he that doth respect mens persons &amp; is such a one fit to Judge for God yea or nay who is out of the humility is not such a one out of the honour for the honour goes before the humility which God requires to be done as to doe Justice and Judgement and love mercy, and this is to be done without respect of persons and the hat not mentioned and is not the ground of rage, and fury and persecution, proceeding from that nature which is in the transgression which respects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and the hatt doth any respect either person or hatt but who are in the transgression; or will any but such who are in the transgression? and so convinced to be, by the Law of God transgressors which will not doe Judgement nor Justice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the hatt be bowed, and that be respected; and whether the hat be not a thing of nought and a dead thing and the Law which is the light is not to be looked at more which respects no mans person and whether this be not honorable whether are not such as are in the transgression dead in sins, and so come to respect han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy works and dead things, and looke at them more then the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law which is living and if that be not bowed, here is the rage and fury stirred up of him who is in the transgession, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects the handy work the hatt before mentioned, which if it be bowed and the person respected, and the righteous Law transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the transgressor rageth not then at the transgressor, but loveth its owne is it not the transgressor of the Law of God that respects persons, and would have others to transgresse which if not they rage, is not that which doth transgresse, which doth rage at the other which will not transgresse but rejoyceth in the Law of the Lord and in that Law exerciseth himselfe day and night, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in it which saith thou shalt not respect mens persons but seeth him that doth comit sin.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116518:5"/>
            <p> And this is he that groweth up like a tree planted by the River of water, whose leafe never fades; and this is he who delighteth in the Law of the Lord, and maketh it his delight, at whom the wicked rages and the Heathen take Counsell together to destroy them that be of upright heart, and all these are as the sheep for the slaughter: By whom is the glory robbed, or of whom of them that be in the transgression, or of God? doth the hat bowing and respecting mens persons overthrow Government in all Courts, and overthrow Laws? or doth it not stir up the prejudice and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and rage, and malice, and manifest that (which casts the Law of God away) the anger wherein is the sin, and manifest the evill Government, the headinesse and passionatenesse that cannot go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it selfe without hats be bowed and persons respected? and is not he that is here from the Spirit of the Lord, which leads to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his Law, which respects no mans person, and from that which should govern him and so mortifie the contrary? Doth not the ill Government proceed from that which respects persons, and looks at an Image as bowing the hat? and doe not men while they are here, acting and practising this feigned humility and complement, forget the Lord, to whom the honour belongs, and bowing the hat, and respecting mens persons with a kind of feigned humility to one anothers face, envying in their heart, hating and biting, and envying one another behind one anothers backs? this is the issue of the worlds Complement.</p>
            <p>Is it not Justice and the perfect Law of God, that respects no mans person, and Judgement, that must rule men, and rule Courts, and will not this perfect Law and Judgement stand, when this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting of hats and persons ceaseth? at this will them that fear God cry yea: And are not these the weightier matters to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked after, Judgement, Equity, and Righteousnesse, and the perfect Law of God that respects no mans person, without the look at the bowing the hat respecting the person? what is it to Judge with partiality, doth he regard the Law of God, Gods Law and the weightier matters, Mercy, Judgement, Justice and Faith, that if the hat be not to him bowed he will Fine him? doth not this shew a worse state then the Pharisee, more in the Earthly black darknes, in the rash presumption, without the fear of God, not regarding his Law? was not the Pharisees rebuked for neglecting the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier matter, when they stood up as in doing the smaller? will not this be a great rebuke to the men of this age, which hath outstrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116518:6"/>them, which hath neglected the greater and weightter, and turned themselves to a complement, a fashion of their own, of the the world, which if not bowing there is a Fine upon them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned; can any one that fears God behold these things without griefe? to see that here is the wisdome of the wise now comes to be confounded with such a base thing, and Justice is turned away for a thing of naught, the understanding of the prudent that a hat should deface it, that the bowing of the hat the outward; &amp; do not you shew here that you mind that complementing more then the Spirit of the Lord, which not bowing to, and bowing it, sets men in such a rage? doth not this shew the blacknesse and darkness stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Read this without prejudice and rage, and persecute not him that is born of the Spirit, and with it covered, who cannot to it bow, which is covered but not with the Spirit of the Lord: And is not the fruits of the flesh wrath, and respecting persons, and bowing the hat? is not that the flesh that would have it bowed down unto, seeing that <hi>Mordichai</hi> could not bow to <hi>Haman,</hi> which did own the righteous Law of God which governed him, which governed not <hi>Haman</hi> which would have been bowed to, and this righteous Law wh ch kept him was to govern all the families of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and was not the King that was among them the Governour to abide in this Law of God which respects no mans person, &amp; to do Justice and Judgement without partiality? and was there not Elders, and Assemblies among whom this Law was, which said, they should not respect persons, and would they? not respecting the persons or bowing the hat destroy them all; or whether were they not destroyed for neglecting the Law, and so scattered among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and there bowing to their handy works? and was not there the respecting of persons, and the Law of God transgressed? and did not such destroy that was in the transgression the Prophets of God? such as had the words of the Scriptures but out of the life of it, out of the life of that Spirit that gave it forth, and so cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with another spirit, shewing the birth born of the flesh, and with that covered, persecuting him that is born of the Spirit, and with that covered; and is not here each birth and each covering seen, and are not all respecters of persons Judged in the sight of God with this Law.</p>
            <p>What is it to seek honour one of another? or what is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that is seeked? and is not this honour delightfull to the flesh, and raiseth up the joy and the glorying in it, if it be given, or if it be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116518:6"/>seeked, and have not many found this honour who have seeked it one of another, and is not this the mark that while you have been here you have been all unbelievers, and cannot believe while you seek the honour one from another, and are not they that have this honour full full of rage, fury and prejudice, and working mischief, plotting in their minds against them that this honour of you seeks not which believes in Christ Jesus, and seeks the honour which comes from God onely, and where this honour is seeked which comes from God onely, and this honour is found, he that hath found it gives the honour to whom the honour belongs (mark take notice here) see, honour to whom honour, and fear to whom fear, custome to whom custome, and this is a good custome, for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes of the Heathen are vaine, and is not that honour which men seeks (to be denyed) one of another, that men might come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and seek the honour that comes from God onely; and are not they that seek honour one of another, they that respect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and they that would have the hat bowed, and if they be in Authority, without the fear of God, to Prison with them, and if they have not Authority full of rage.</p>
            <p>And is not this a manifestation that the Spirit of God is in Prison in them, and imprisoned with that which doth imprison them that cannot bow to them, and cannot transgresse Gods Law but in it delights? doth not this shew the Magistrate, and the power without the fear of the Lord? and them that be in his fear regarding his Law, and power, and Authority, did ever any of them that were born of the Spirit, which did Minister to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in Prison, which had the Royall Law of God, Prison and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and Fine, any that would not respect their person, and their hats bow to them? and is not the Spirit in the Prison in him that would have his person respected, and the hat bowed to him? and doe you not believe that God will bow that, and make that to bow with his righteous Law, which righteous Law shall answer that which hath been imprisoned with the respecter of persons and the hat, which in the transgression hath lived.</p>
            <p>Where these things are standing, the bowing of the hat, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son respected, &amp; so men cast into Prison for not bowing of the hat, who mind the weightier matters; is the understanding of the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent yet brought to naught, that so much looks at the bowing of the hat, &amp; the person respected? is your prudence, is your understanding here brought to naught yet (mark, take notice) is not your wisdom
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116518:7"/>standing, which must be confounded with a base thing, and things that are not brings to naught things that are, (mark &amp; take notice) where is the wisdome of the wise where is the understanding of the prudent, hath God chosen the base things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the things that are mighty, (mark) the base things of the world to confound the mighty, and to bring to naught the things that are, and this we see fulfilled and fulfilling, to him be glory whose Arme is stretched out; where is the wisdome of the wise, where is the understanding of the prudent, where is the Scribe and where is the disputer? so, hath not God made foolishnesse the wisdome of the world? and such as are foolish are out of the light which comes from the wisdome of God, and such as be in the light the wisdome of God, are out of the worlds foolish wisdome, and the understanding of the prudent, and seeks the honour and the glory that comes from God onely, and such as honours the Son, the Son honours which comes to abide in his Doctrine, who is not of the world, but from the world seperates, and brings to testifie against the world that their works are evill, and therefore the world hates the Light and hates them who be in the Light. And this shall be their condemnation (the Light) to this Light I am manifest, in every mans conscience in the sight of God, and this is the word of the Lord God to you.</p>
            <p>Are not they covered but not with the Spirit of the Lord that are offended that their persons are not tespected and the hat not to them bowed, are not these in the transgression out of the Law of God yea or nay? <hi>David</hi> who was a King bowed the heart of all the men of <hi>Judah</hi> even as the heart of one man, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. but it is not said there, that he bowed their hats. And <hi>David</hi> the King had his head covered, and all the people that was with him cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red every man his head, (mark) all the People that was with the King had their heads covered, who was a man after Gods own heart, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. And <hi>David</hi> speaks of such who were wicked Oppressors and deadly enemies, who are inclosed in their own fat, whose mouths spoke proudly, these have set their eyes to bow down to the Earth, which is like a Lyon greedy of his prey, which <hi>David</hi> prayed to the Lord for disappointing of such, <hi>Psal.</hi> 17. And <hi>Moses</hi> said to <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Eleazer</hi> and <hi>Ithamar</hi> his sons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover not your heads neither rent your cloths least you dye, and least wrath come upon all the People, but let your Brethren the whole house of <hi>Israel</hi> bewaile the burning which the Lord hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116518:7"/>kindled, here was a bewayling and yet covered, a command of <hi>Moses</hi> the servant of God, and a Judge of all <hi>Israel,</hi> not to unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their heads. <hi>David</hi> it saith made them bow their hearts, but where is it said that <hi>David</hi> made them bow their hats? <hi>Naaman</hi> who saw the evill of the worship and the bowing in the house of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> for the which thing he asked pardon when his Master leaned on his hand and he bowed himselfe, now he that had tasted something of the Lord saw beyond that worship, and the evill of that bowing: So all you that set up a worship of your own, houses ordained for Popery, and Idolls Temples, is not that as bad amongst you that worship not God in Spirit? yea, it is seen so with them that worship God in Spirit, and knowes his power, and to him bowes, and is there not many of you that doth goe to those houses to worship and there to bow, in the state of <hi>Naaman</hi> in fear, and desires a pardon in that thing, when that you goe with your Masters and Mistresses as <hi>Naaman</hi> did, and bow? but all you that doe goe thither to worship, doe you not appear to be out of the Prophets life, which is a life high above all the world? He that is called being a servant is the Lords free-man, and he that is called being free is Christs servant, ye are bought with a price, therefore be ye not the servants of men, But fear the Lord, fear to whom fear, sanctifie the Lord of hosts and let him be your fear, <hi>Isa.</hi> 8. The fear of man brings a snare, but who so putteth his trust in the Lord shall be safe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.25. Cursed be he that trusteth in man, and maketh flesh his Arme, and whose heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>And furious <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> cast the three Children into his fiery Furnace, because they could not bow down to his Image which he had set up, and bound them in their coats and in their hosen, and with their hats on, and other garments, into the fiery Furnace: Now <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> fury was not for their not doffing their hats, but for not bowing down to his Image which he had set up; Which in these dayes it appears worse with the men of this age, who are so full of rage and fury because they have not the hat bowed to them, and for prisoning and persecuting and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them for not bowing the hat unto them; it is such a thing fallen out in this age which will be upon Record, as never was in all ages since the world began, not bowing the hat an Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a Fine is imposed upon them; and this is done amongst them that call themselves Christians, which they that be Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116518:8"/>be out of the doctrines that perish. And will not a hat perish and passe away, and that which doth respect mens persons, and would have their persons respected, whether that doth not perish likewise, that is so much eyed and looked at with the men of the world in these dayes.</p>
            <p>And whether the Law of God the higher Power which the soule must be subject to, shall perish; and whether that was not before hats were; and whether this Law doth not require that to bow which respects hats and persons, and so makes the heart to bow; and whether the hat is not a toy and a bable, a comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and an unperfect thing, in respect of the Royall Law of God which is perfect and endures for ever?</p>
            <p>Whether hath not the world such a kind of bowing now, as those wicked ones had to Christ, who bowed their knee in spight and derision, and spit upon him; and doth not some bow their knee in pretence to him now, and put him in Prison where he is made manifest?</p>
            <p>And bowing the hat which is a thing that will please men in this age, or displease them, if it be not bowed they are full of rage.</p>
            <p>Here all may see what a toy they are carried away withall, and what toyes will please men or displease them, even a complement and a toy which pleaseth children, and while such a complement doth offend, this shewes abundance of weaknesse and the want of humility which is required, and wants <hi>Moses</hi> meeknesse and the Royall Law of God.</p>
            <p>For Toyes, Complements and Bables, carries men from se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riousnesse and sincerity; for doth it not make it manifest here that Toyes and Bables have eaten up the sincerity that should be amongst men, for while they are eying of those things they forget the Lord, while the eye is carryed after the bowing of a handy work, which if it to them be not bowed which would have it they be in a rage.</p>
            <p>The Heathens did rage whose customes were vaine, they whose soules were subject to the higher power turned away from the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes of the Heathen which are vaine; and was not the Lords hand turned against such that bowed to the customes of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and the works of mens hands: And is not the Hat a work of mens hand, which must now be bowed, else a Prison and a Fine is laid upon them, by them that be out of the fear of the Lord; and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116518:8"/>doe not you believe that God will throw dovvn all those things, that people shall not imprison one another for complements and handy vvorks of men? And doe you not believe that the Lord is unclothing, and taking off the garments, and making every one to appear in their ovvn likenesse? And vvhat is it to judge by the outvvard appearance, and vvhat is it to Judge Righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is not this it vvhich ansvvers that of God in every mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and respects no mans person, not bovving the hat nor looking for it, but bovving the heart, as <hi>David</hi> did the hearts of the people? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>I am the Light of the vvorld (saith Christ) and doth enlighten every man that cometh into the vvorld, vvhich if you love the Light you love Christ, and it vvill bring you from the vvorld, and from their Fashions and Complements, and not to be conformable to the vvorld but to have your minds renevved, and such as are here the vvorld hates, vvho are the servants of the Lord, and are the obedient children, and are transformed by the renewing of their minds, and such the world hates, and such who are hated doth not mervaile, because they cannot be conformable to them, but testifies against the world because their works are evill, and this was the cause that they hated him, who was not of the world, and likewise is the cause why all are hated now, vvhich be in him.</p>
            <p>Hovv many Honours be there that the Scripture speaks of, vvhether there be any but tvvo, one that is seeked from God, and vvhether the other be not the Honour that <hi>Balak</hi> vvould have promoted <hi>Balaam</hi> vvith, yea or nay?</p>
            <p>Whether Honour be not to a fool as a parable in his mouth?</p>
            <p>And saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> As snow in the summer and as raine in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest, so Honour is not seemly for a fool, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26</p>
            <p>And if so, whether it be not that which is from the Spirit (to it) contrary?</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>